Guide to the Ralph E. Griswold Collection, GWSM, Inc., 1912-1988 AIS.2001.10
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Ralph E. Griswold, GWSM, Inc. Collection
1912-1988
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Griswold, Ralph E.
AIS.2001.10
30.6 Linear Feet (73 boxes)
This collection documents the research, activities, and projects undertaken by landscape architect Ralph E. Griswold, founder of Griswold, Winters, Swain, & Mullin (GWSM), Inc., landscape architecture firm of Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania. The materials in this collection range from 1917 to 1981 and include personal documents and regional, national and international project files. The Griswold collection contains plans, drawings, blueprints, photographs, slides, glass plate negatives, diaries, and correspondence. The materials mainly relate to Griswold's individual landscape work, however some of the project from GWSM are also included.
Biography
Ralph E. Griswold began his career as a landscape architect in 1916 after graduating from Cornell University, where he received both his bachelors and masters degrees in landscape architecture. Following his graduation, Griswold served in World War I as a camouflage officer stationed in France. In 1919, Griswold was a part of Bryant F. Fleming landscape architecture firm in Buffalo, New York. Subsequently, Griswold won the Prix de Rome, a competitive scholarship organized by the Royal Academy of Painting and Sculpture in 1920. He spent the next three years at the American Academy in Rome as a Fellow of Landscape Architecture with Frederick Law Olmstead, Jr. as his advisor. After returning to the United States with his family in 1923, Griswold joined the architecture firm of A.D. Taylor in Cleveland, Ohio, and later moved to Pittsburgh in 1927 to establish his own firm of GWSM, Inc.
Between 1934 and 1945, Griswold worked as the superintendent for the Bureau of Parks in Pittsburgh. He contributed to many significant Pittsburgh projects, including Point State Park, the Pittsburgh Zoo, Chatham Village, Grandview Overlook, and the Sewickley Memorial. Griswold also worked on side projects with corporate and residential landscapes throughout the Pittsburgh area, including many country club and park projects.
During this time, Griswold also contributed to landscape planning projects abroad, including the American Cemetery in Anzio, Italy, and the Archaeological Park at the excavation of the Agora in Athens, Greece. Between 1956 and 1958, Griswold continued his historic landscape research as the first Research Fellow with the Dumbarton Oaks Project at Harvard University. While semi-retired from GWSM, Inc. in the 1960s and 1970s, he lived in Williamsburg, Virginia, and worked on various projects including research for the gardens of Colonial Williamsburg, Mary Washington House, and Monticello. Griswold also contributed to other notable projects such as Rosenwald Estates, William Penn's Pennsbury Manor, the University of Pittsburgh's Falk Clinic, and many private residences in Pennsylvania and Virginia.
Scope and Content Note
The Ralph E. Griswold, GWSM, Inc. collection contains project materials and drawings by Ralph E. Griswold (1894-1981), founder of the GSWM landscape architecture firm in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania. The materials range from 1912 to 1981. Griswold maintained records throughout his life that document his career as a noted landscape architect. In addition, this collection contains materials that illustrate the variety of projects researched and fulfilled by Griswold and his company, GWSM, Inc. There is also material that notes the collaboration of world heritage landscape projects, such as the Agora in Athens and the American Cemetery in Anzio, Italy. The majority of the material was kept in Griswold's original or working order. Types of documentation contained in the collection include research and lecture notes, newspaper clippings, articles, correspondence, diaries, receipts, publications, blueprints, plans, photographic material, and sketches. Series VI (Boxes 34-46) is stored separately, as are the oversize media materials.
Arrangement
Series I. Personal Material, 1917-1981
Series II. Diaries, 1912-1916, 1946-1981
Series III. Lecture Notes and Unpublished Works, 1913-1944
Series IV. Reference Material
Series V. Project Material, 1917-1976
Series VI. Media Material
Series VII. Blue Prints and Oversized material, 1930-1988
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mr. Tom Borellis on behalf of GWSM, Inc. on October 16, 2001.
Previous Citation
Ralph E. Griswold, GWSM, Inc. Collection, 1912-1988, AIS.2001.10, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh.
Separated Material
The media material of Series VI (boxes 34-46) is stored separately, as are the oversize media materials which are stored in flat files.
Rome (Italy); Williamsburg (Va.); Personal papers; Pittsburgh (Pa.); Business and Industry; Landscape gardening; Architecture; Landscape architecture; Landscape architectural projects; Architectural drawings (Visual works); Athens (Greece); Anzio (Italy); Griswold, Ralph E.; GWSM, Inc.
- Personal Files, 1917-1945; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series consists of material documenting the intertwined personal and professional life of Ralph E. Griswold. Griswold's personal and professional lives coalesce in his dedication and interest in the field of landscape architecture. The materials in this series describe a portion of Griswold's academic and WWI military records, while receipts and mortgage statements document some of his financial history. Griswold attended the American E. F. Art Training Centre in Paris at the conclusion of WWI. Paintings and pencil sketches of villa and ship scenes created by Griswold are part of his personal collection. Griswold also collected many small national and international publications regarding landscape training and architecture which are included in the series.
  - Army Records, 1917-1943 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Academy Photographs, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Financial Statements, 1935-1939 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Griswold Estate Settlement, 1935-1941 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Warren Odd Fellows Temple Co. Stock Correspondence, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Valley City Mortgage Co. Correspondence, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Receipts, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Civilian Defense Awards, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Ralph E. Griswold water color painting ship scene, undated (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Ralph E. Griswold water color painting villa scene, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Pencil sketch booklet, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Notes and Interpretation on Aero plane Photography during World War I, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Point of Empire: An Epic Struggle of the 1700s, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - American Architect and Architecture, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - The Architectural Forum, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Stephen Collins Foster Memorial of the University of Pittsburgh, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Report of the American E. F. Art Training Centre, March – June 1919 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Memories of Art Archaeology, April 1904 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Sloane's House of Today: at the Century of Progress Exposition, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - The Evolution of the City of Rome from its Origin to the Gallic Catastrophe, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - A Cathedral Hillside and its Gardens, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - La Vie Urbaine, 1923 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Wild Flowers of the Old Bay State, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Harpers Magazine, December, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Pennsylvania Folk Festival, Bucknell University, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Diaries, 1912-1917, 1946-1981; II.
  Griswold methodically documented his life, writing entries on social and business relationships as well as existing projects. His earliest diaries, dating from 1914 through 1917, describe day-to-day affairs such as schooling and social relationships. Later diaries show the evolution of his entries into subjects based on current projects, which are detailed in Series V, during his professional career in the 1940s and 1950s. Griswold adopted a more leisurely approach in the 1970s and 1980s, focusing on his personal life to a greater degree than in any previous diary. Most diaries also contain fiscal expenditures, phone-lists, and tabulations in addition to personal antecedents and opinions of his associates. These diaries record a mixture of personal and professional experiences during two distinct periods in Griswold's life, written in the periods from 1914-1917 and 1946-1981.
  - 1912-1917 (Box 4, Volume 1)
  - 1946-1954 (Box 4, Volume 2-10)
  - 1955-1963 (Box 5, Volume 11-19)
  - 1964-1972 (Box 6, Volume 20-28)
  - 1973-1981 (Box 7, Volume 29-37)
- Lecture Notes and Unpublished Works, 1913-1944; III.
  Griswold dedication to the landscape architecture field is evident through his diligent notes that he wrote from lectures over the years. The lecture notes describe projects, plans, facts, and theories on landscape architecture. Griswold accumulated lecture notes during his time at Cornell University as well as other conferences and speeches he attended. It is evident that Griswold felt that he could repurpose his notes for future research and conference material. Some of the lecture notes and unpublished works were used in a variety of conferences and speaking engagements given by Griswold. Griswold notes include ideas for speeches, key points of lectures, conference material, and sketches of landscapes. Frequently, these notes directly correspond to a particular landscape project Griswold had worked on. The material in this series date from 1913 to 1944. Additional files relating to lectures and projects may be found in Series VII.
  - Landscape Art #3 Lecture Notes, 1913 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Landscape Art #4 Lecture Notes, 1914-1915 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Old as the Hills and as Beautiful, 1922 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Villa Cicogna, 1923 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - A Synopsis of Lectures on Landscape Architecture, Cleveland School of Art, 1924 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Italian Gardening, 1924 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - The Villa Caprarola and Its Traditions, 1922-1924 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - The Hillside Home of H.B. Higgins, 1932 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Parks and Playgrounds: Their Uses and Their Planning, 1939 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Regional Recreation as a Metropolitan Necessity, 1939 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Talk by Ralph E. Griswold, Pittsburgh Regional Planning Association, 1940 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Planting Bigelow Boulevard, Pittsburgh, 1941 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - What the Air Raid Warden Service is Doing, 1942 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - The Planting of Trees as War Memorials, 1944 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Landscape Architecture, undated (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Individuality in Landscape Character, undated (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Landscape Planting in the Grand Manner of the Renaissance, undated (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Landscape Studies by Motor, undated (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Looking Into the Future of Pittsburgh Parks, undated (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - The Contribution of Natural Science to the General Welfare, undated (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - The Bureau of Parks: Its Functions and Operation, undated (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Board of Parks and Recreation, undated (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Character in the Garden, undated (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - To What Extent Has Landscape Architecture Been Modern Since the Renaissance, undated (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Italian Gardening and its Relation to the Profession of Landscape Architecture, undated (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - The Meaning of an Academy Fellowship, undated (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Synopsis of Talks to be given in Class Room, undated (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - The Use of Water in Garden Composition, undated (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - The Adaptation of Physical Beauty, undated (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - The Development of a Garden Scheme, undated (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - History of Gardening, undated (Box 8, Folder 31)
  - Comprehensive Vision in Landscape Design, undated (Box 8, Folder 32)
  - Parks and Recreation Painting for Boroughs and Townships, undated (Box 8, Folder 33)
  - The Future of the Arts and Crafts Center, undated (Box 8, Folder 34)
  - The Architectural Value of Paths, Background, Walls, Water, Etc., undated (Box 8, Folder 35)
  - Extracts from Charles Eliot, Landscape Architect, undated (Box 8, Folder 36)
  - Pittsburgh: A Place to Live and Work, undated (Box 8, Folder 37)
  - Landscape Lecture Speaking Note Cards, undated (Box 8, Folder 38)
  - An Outline for the Analysis of Garden Design, undated (Box 8, Folder 39)
  - Elements of Character in Landscape Design, undated (Box 8, Folder 40)
  - Gardening: A Fine Art, undated (Box 8, Folder 41)
  - Directions in American Painting, undated (Box 8, Folder 42)
  - Notes and Extracts Relating to Versailles, Chantilly and Ermenville, undated (Box 8, Folder 43)
- Reference Materials, undated; IV.
  This series contains materials collected to facilitate Griswold's landscape architecture designs. The majority of these materials are reference photographs of a variety of structures and architectural details, mainly of Italian and American origin. Sketches and photographs are organized into architectural form files such as balustrades, villas, and interiors, which were later used as references for his work. The reference materials retained the original order and labeling in the manner it was received. Included in this series are photographs, sketches, plans, blueprints, layouts, and articles. The majority of the reference material are undated.
  - Fountains, Well Heads, and Cascades (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
  - Paintings (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Arches and Colonnades (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Italian Villas (Box 9, Folder 5-6)
  - Italian Villas and Facades (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Villa Catena (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Windows, Doors, and Columns (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Courtyards and Loggia (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Architectural Interiors (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Bridges (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Piazzas (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Rubbings and Watercolors (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Measured Details of Villa Caprarola (Box 10, Folder 01-02)
  - Measured Details of Villa Cicogna (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Measured Details from Frascati, Italy (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Measured Details from Italy (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Measured Details of Facades and Villas (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Measured Details of Balustrades (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Measured Details of Steps (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Steps and Balustrades (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Well Heads (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Iron Railings (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Iron Works (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Gateways (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Sculpture and Vases (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Cemeteries, undate (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Cartouches (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Flower Shows (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Gateways (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - General and Theses (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - General Landscape (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Plans and Exhibit Prints (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Edward Capps Memorial Lectern (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - E. W. Mathews Landscape (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Fox Chapel Club Fountain (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Albert D. Taylor Plans and Photographs (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Albert D. Taylor Photographs (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - H.B. Higgins Photographs (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - R.A. Hunt Photographs (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - B.D. Phillips Photographs (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - J.E. Lewis Photographs (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Julius Fleischman Garden Photographs (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Dr. Bowman Landscape Photographs (Box 11, Folder 19)
- Project Files, 1917-1976; V.
  The majority of Griswold's professional material revolve around his architectural landscape projects both in the United State and abroad. Some of these files contain documentary photographs, including many from his work on the Athenian Agora during the 1950s. Some of the highlighted works are the Agora project, the Anzio Cemetery, the Jones & Laughlin Steel Company town revitalization, and the Mellon-Scaife Botanical Garden. The items in this series span the years from 1917 to 1976. Included are plans, blueprints, layouts, drafts of articles and speeches, news clippings, professional correspondence, and information about Griswold's projects. Projects details and dates are also mentioned in the diary entries in Series II. Additional files relating to this materials may be found in Series VII.
  - Jones & Laughlin Steel Company Town Revitalization, 1946-1948; 1.
    A project of local significance to Pittsburgh was the Jones & Laughlin Steel Company town revitalization. Jones & Laughlin Steel hired Griswold for the recreation and restoration of many of its company towns throughout western and central Pennsylvania, which produced much of the coal and coke used in the production of steel. Griswold was consulted to head the revitalization project in the company towns of Vestaburgh, Richeyville, Bobtown, Blairton, and Denbo; he completed these revitalization projects between 1946 and 1947.
    - Jones & Laughlin Steel Corporation- Report on landscape and recreation improvement of company towns, 1946-1947 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Jones & Laughlin Steel- Vestaburgh, 1946 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Jones & Laughlin Steel- Richeyville, 1946 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Jones & Laughlin Steel- Bobtown, 1946 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Jones & Laughlin Steel- Blairton, 1946 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Jones & Laughlin Steel- Denbo, 1947 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Jones & Laughlin Steel, 1946-1948 (Box 12, Folder 7-10)
  - Anzio Cemetery Project, 1949-1955; 2.
    The World War II Sicily-Rome American Cemetery and Memorial, built in Italy to commemorate Americans who died during the liberation of Axis Nation Italy, was directed by the United States War Commission, which oversaw the overall design, construction, sculpture, and landscaping work necessary for the site. A wide central mall leads to the memorial, adorned with works of art and architecture, emblematic of America's reverence for the fallen war dead. Architects for the cemetery and memorial were Gugler, Kimball and Husted of New York City. Ralph Griswold was tapped by the commission to act as landscape architect; this became his first major landscaping work overseas. Griswold spent much of his time drawing plans, developing planting plans, writing and answering correspondence, and working with the War Commission in efforts to construct the memorial.
    Griswold designed the entrance road to the Anzio Cemetery, lining the path with neatly-trimmed hedges. There is a large elliptical shaped reflecting pool with a small island at its center. Griswold chose to plant several Italian cypress trees which flank the stone cenotaph on the island. Evergreen holly oak trees and hedges line the wide grassy mall through the graves area from the reflecting pool to the memorial. The larger garden north of the memorial is planted with beds of polyanthus roses, geraniums, white oleander, purple bougainvillea and other flowers in parterre arrangements. The permanent cemetery and memorial were completed in 1956. The material in this subseries dates from 1949 to 1955.
    - Anzio Cemetery, Correspondence, 1949-1955 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Anzio Cemetery, Correspondence, 1950 (Box 13, Folder 2-6)
    - Anzio Cemetery, Plans and Blueprints, 1950-1951 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Anzio Cemetery, Correspondence, 1951 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Anzio Cemetery, Correspondence and Plan, 1952 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Anzio Cemetery, Correspondence, 1953-1956 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Anzio Cemetery, Inspection and Photographs, 1966-1968 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Anzio Cemetery Letters, Photographs, Postcards, and News Clippings, 1952-1965 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Agora Material, 1950-1956; 3.
    The American School of Classical Studies in Athens has been a premier center for the study of Greek civilization since its inception in 1881. It has proved to be not only a center for teaching, but the heart of American excavations of antiquity in Greece, with the resulting published material forming the basis of classical study today. In 1931, the school began work on their most significant find, the ancient Greek Agora in the city of Athens. Since 3000 B.C.E., this ancient marketplace served as the confluence of Athenian economic, political, and social practices, and emerged as the physical manifestation of the famous democracy of Athens around the fifth century B.C.E. The grounds, where ancient citizens held public office and elections, would influence Western Civilization for centuries to come.
    By 1957, the first archeological park in Europe was developed to showcase the work of the Agora excavation from the previous decades. The landscaping for this presentation proved to be a challenging and novel undertaking. The school director, Homer Thompson, began talks with Ralph E. Griswold in 1950 to act as supervisor of the new park. His work included not only making the park serviceable by adding benches, creating entrances, and clearing ruin, but aesthetically pleasing by adorning the surrounding hillside and park with historically and culturally relevant foliage and trees. He was responsible not only for the logistic constraints of an operation in the dry environment of Attica, but charged with conforming to stringent academic standards of recreating the ancient marketplace. Griswold also coordinated with American and Greek donations for the landscape work, budgeting and researching most of the sites' expenses. During his long involvement with the project, he developed a lasting relationship and correspondence with Homer Thompson and much of the staff of the American School of Classical Studies. The project was completed between 1950 and 1955; the park was dedicated in 1956. The material in this subseries dates form 1950 to 1956.
    - Agora Correspondence, 1950-1955 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Agora Photographs and Reference Drawings, 1952-1953 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Agora Photographs, Correspondence, and Plant Lists, 1952-1967 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Agora Preliminary Report, 1953 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Agora Reports, 1953 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Agora Excavation Plan, 1953 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Agora Correspondence and Personnel Lists, 1953-1956 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Agora Correspondence and Article Drafts, 1954 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Agora Memorial Fountain, 1954 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Agora Church of the Holy Apostles, 1954-1955 (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Agora Budget, 1954-1955 (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - Agora Business Agreement, 1950-1956 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Agora Plans and Layouts, 1954-1956 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Agora Temple of Haphaistos Label Order, 1955 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Agora Planting, Correspondence, and Notes, 1955-1956 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Agora Correspondence and Press Clippings, 1955-1957 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Agora Faucets, 1956-1957 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Agora Correspondence, 1956-1957 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Archeological Landscape Pioneering, 1957 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Agora Correspondence, Maps, and Notes, 1957-1962 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Agora Correspondence, Press, and News Clippings, 1957-1967 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Agora Photographs, Negatives, Plans, Articles, Landscape Architecture, 1957-1967 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Agora Correspondence, 1966 (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Agora Plant Lists, undated (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Archeological Institute of America and Lucy Shoe Correspondence, 1953-1955 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Garden Club of Virginia Material, undated; 4.